# 大家好 聽說兄弟十幾年前就檢了好多那個隕石哦
Hi everyone! I heard that my buddy has started collecting the, the meteorites a dozen of years ago.
# 我們去看一下 這是他家的果園
Let’s take a look! This is his orchard.
# 一片一片的 都是
The whole area. They're all,
# 現在都黃啦 等下來
they’re now becoming ripe. Later!
# 不急 不急 不急
No hurry, no hurry, no hurry
# 這個就是鐵隕石呀
These are all iron meteorites.
# 鐵隕石
Iron meteorites
# 嗯
Yup
# 好重啊 這個
It’s really heavy, this one.
# 是 跟石頭一樣沒區別
Yea. It’s essentially the same as rock.
# 每個都好重
Each one is really heavy.
# 是啊
Yup!
# 在哪裡撿的
Where did you pick them?
# 在貴州那邊啊
Somewhere in Guizhou
# 貴州
Guizhou
# 是啊
Yup
# 我們這邊好像很少哦
They seem to be rather rare here.
# 沒有 沒有
No. no.
# 沒有
No
# 嗯 根本上就沒有
Um. Not at all.
# 這個不是甚麼地方都有的
It’s not something that you can find everywhere.
# 看就石頭一樣
They look like rocks.
# 是
Yup
# 真正是是鐵
But they’re actually iron.
# 你看 這裡 跟鐵一樣的哦 生鐵一樣
Look! Here! It looks like iron, you know, like pig iron.
# 這邊 你看 被敲了一下
Here. Look! It has been knocked.
# 敲了一下有反光
It’s shiny after being knocked.
# 它這給那個風吹雨打呀 它不會跟那個鐵一樣
It was exposed to the nature. You know, so it doesn’t look like iron.
# 它就那個光面很好
It’s like, the surface is really shiny.
# 它會曝光 曝的很滑很光滑
It shines. It shines, it means it’s smooth. Really shiny.
# 你現在我放在家裡有七八年啦
It has been with me for seven or eight years now.
# 是不是(所以?)這個光面沒有 沒有沒釉面就不見啦
So it’s not shining. I mean, the shiny surface is not here any more.
# 它又 又該風吹兩打 就跟那個鐵你給風吹雨打它就會瘦(?)的
And ah… it’s exposed to the nature. If it's iron, if it’s exposed to the nature, it would be roosted.
# 它會生鏽
It would be rusted.
# 嗯 它這個就不會的
Um! But not this one.
# 這個不會
Not this one.
# 嗯 越曬越那個光面越好的這個
Um! The more it’s exposed to sunshine, the shinier it is.
# 越曬越亮
Sunshine makes it shinier.
# 是啊 越曬越亮
Exactly, sunshine makes it shinier.
# 從天上掉下來 那麼大塊
It dropped from the sky. So big.
# 很少見
It’s really rare.
# 我們這邊幾乎都看不到
We hardly see any these things here.
# 沒有 根本上沒有
No. Not at all.
# 根本上沒有
Not at all
# 是啊
Nope
# 很漂亮
It’s really pretty.
# 本身我就收藏 我自己收藏很多石頭
In fact I collect, I collect a lot of these kind of rocks myself.
# 你 你收藏啊
You, you mean you collect them?
# 是啊
Yup
# 這幾個都是寶貝喲
These are your treasures.
# 嗯 是啊 家裡收藏的都是的 那玉石啊
Um! Yea! And so are my collections at home. The jades, for example
# 還有那個
And also the, you know
# 雞血玉呀 都很多 家裡都收藏的很多
the red jadeite, a lot! I have a lot of collections at home.
# 收藏愛好者
You’re a collector.
# 你就自己在上這樣檢啊
So you just pick them my yourselves?
# 嗯
Um!
# 多不多
You have a lot?
# 沒有 多的話就不值錢啦
No! They wouldn’t be worth anything if there are a lot.
# 這個不是那
It’s not like…
# 可遇不可求這個東西
You can’t find it. Fate brings it to you.
# 這個是
It’s ah…
# 這個是可遇不可求的事情
You can’t find it. Fate brings it to you.
# 是啊 嗯
Yea!
Um!
# 這個是 鐵 鐵隕石
It’s, it’s iron, iron meteorite.
# 它也好重 是啊 我們看不出來
It’s really heavy. Yea. We can’t say anything about it.
# 要專家才看得出來
Only an expert can.
# 快點把它收好來 這個是寶貝來的
Alright! Keep them well. These are your treasures.
# 來看一下你家的臍橙
Let’s have a look at your navel oranges.
# 好
Alright!
# 哇 好多哇 現在
Wa! There are a lot now.
# 是 今年臍橙大豐收啦
Yea! This year is a Bumper Yield.
# 大豐收
Bumper Yield
# 嗯 是啊 (時間太短，放在一起)
Um!
Yea!
# 你看 這個果 搞一個來吃一下
Look! This orange… Let’s have one.
# 你看 這個果 不洗都那麼乾淨
Look! This orange, is so clean. We don’t even need to wash it.
# 很漂亮的這個果
It's really pretty, this orange.
# 像這有一點點這個小疤 這個很正常
It’s like a small scar here. It’s very normal.
# 你看 這個皮好薄哇
Look! The peel is really thin.
# 很好吃的 這種臍橙
It’s really tasty, this kind of navel oranges.
# 現在剛剛熟
They’re now newly ripe.
# 應該還有帶點酸酸的 再過半個月的話就不酸啦
So it should be still a little bit sour. The sourness will all be gone in a fortnight.
# 很甜啦
They will then be really sweet.
# 嗯
Um!
# 現在都熟透啦
They’re completely ripe now.
# 很甜哦
It’s so sweet.
# 因為我摘的這個 比較黃
It’s because I’ve picked a more ripe one.
# 大浪費啦
What a waste!
# 這個樹 多的6年啦
This tree, is six years old now.
# 嗯 6年啦
Um! Six years.
# 掛100多斤果
It has more than fifty kilograms of oranges.
# 可以呀 幾百塊錢哦
Not bad. It means several hundred bucks.
# 全都是標準果 今年
All are up to standard, this year.
# 幾乎 幾乎都沒有次果
There are hardly, hardly any substandard ones.
# 是啊 全是標準果
Yup!
All are up to standard.
# 全部是標準果
# 你看 這一大片都是兄弟家的臍橙
Look! The whole area is my buddy’s navel oranges.
# 應該都有幾萬棵
There should be tens of thousands of trees.
# 大部份樹上都有好多的哦 都長了上百斤
And there are a lot of oranges on most of the trees, more than fifty kilograms.
# 這是我們村的產業
These are the product of our village.
# 這邊的稍微青有點 沒有陽光照射
The ones on this side are a bit green, cuz the sunlight can't reach them.
# 它照射的量不是很足 所以青一點
They don’t have enough sunlight. So they’re a bit green.
# 外面那裡好黃啊
The ones outside are golden yellow now.
# 哇 你看這裡 陽光照射比較足的地方就在這裡 都黃了
Wa! Look! It’s where the sunshine can reach. They’re golden yellow now.
# 你看 這裡都可以摘啦 直接可以摘 這麼黃啦 看見沒有
Look! They can be picked now, picked right away. They’re golden yellow now, see?
# 因為這裡有一點點青 有一點點青
Cuz, it’s a tiny little bit green here, a tiny little bit green.
# 這個 其實沒事的這個
It’s ah..In fact it doesn’t matter.
# 摘果的話必須要那個哦
If you wanna pick them, you need to, you know….
# 十一月十號才可以開摘 因為我們這邊
You need to wait until November tenth. Cuz here we…
# 等於說 保 額 為保護那個農戶的利益嘛
It’s like, pro, well, we need to protect the welfare of the farmers.
# 就是統一一天開園 十一月十一月十號
So we all start picking on the same day. November, November tenth.
# 才可以摘 其它時候都不能摘
Not before, not other time.
# 因為如果摘的話 像那個
Cuz if you pick, like…
# 如果這青的摘下來的話就說口感沒有那麼好的
If you pick the green ones, I mean, it won’t taste as good.
# 其實要讓它在樹上黃了 那個口感是最好的
In fact they taste the best if they’re left to become ripe on the trees.
# 這樣能保住 保護這個 贛南臍橙的口感
Then the quality of the Southern Jiangxi Navel Oranges can be pro... can be guaranteed.
# 不然 如果現在摘的話 大家的摘的話 那價格就會亂掉
Otherwise, if somebody starts picking now, if everybody starts picking now, the price might fluctuate a lot.
# 你看這個臍橙 長了個肚臍眼出來
Have a look at this navel orange! Here’s a belly button.
# 很漂亮哦
It’s so pretty.
# 你看這些果 好大啊
Have a lot at these oranges. They're so big.
# 夠大吧這個 你看它肚臍眼 所以它叫臍橙
It’s big isn’t it? Have a look at its belly button. They’s why it’s called navel orange.
# 臍橙 就是那個肚臍眼的臍 臍橙
Navel orange. Navel means belly button. So navel orange.
# 今年好多臍橙啊 都是豐收的
There are a lot of navel oranges this year. It’s a year of Bumper Yield.
# 但受疫情影響 到現在 好多 好多果園都還沒訂出去
But because of the pandemic, now, many, many orchards have hardly received any orders.
# 價格可能也會降 降 降低一點
The price may also drop, drop, drop a bit.
# 但是不影響 不影響它的銷量哦
But the sale is not, is not affected.
# 我們贛南這邊 稀土額 那個土地的微量元素啊
Here in Southern Jiangxi, the rare-earth elements, the minerals in the soil,
# 就是稀土含量比較高 所以種出的臍橙特別好吃
I mean it’s rich in rare-earth. That’s why the navel oranges here are exceptionally tasty.
# 所以 贛南 贛南的臍橙都是出了名的這個
So, navel oranges from Southern Jiangxi, Southern Jiangxi is really famous for,
# 好吃 那叫 叫 叫甚麼 叫微量元素嘛
being tasty. It's called, called, what is it called? It's called minerals, right?
# 就是含稀土比較高
Anyway, I mean the content of rare-earth is rather high.
# 全世界的稀土含量 占比最高的地方
It’s the highest in the world and most of the rare-earth is here.
# 就在我們贛南這一帶
It’s here, in Southern Jiangxi.